Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Now resolved upon a journey
lähteäksensä käkesi
To the cold and dreary regions
tuonne kylmähän kylähän,
Of the gloomy land of Pohja.
pimeähän Pohjolahan.
Then he took his straw-hued stallion
Otti olkisen orihin,
Like a pea-stalk in his colour,
hernevartisen hevosen,
And the golden bit adjusted,
pisti suitset kullan suuhun,
Bridle on his head of silver,
päitsensä hopean päähän:
On his back himself he seated,
itse istuvi selälle,
And he started on his journey,
löihe reisin ratsahille.
And he trotted gently onward,
Ajoa hyryttelevi,
At an easy pace he journeyed,
matkoansa mittelevi
Mounted on the straw-hued courser,
orihilla olkisella,
Like a pea-stalk in his colour.
hernevarrella hevolla.
Thus through Väinölä he journeyed,
Ajoi Väinölän ahoja,
Over Kalevala's wide heathlands,
Kalevalan kankahia:
And the horse made rapid progress,
hepo juoksi, matka joutui,
Home behind, and journey shortened,
koti jääpi, tie lyheni.
Then across the sea he journeyed,
Jo ajoi meren selälle,
O'er the far-extending billows,
ulapalle aukealle
With the horse's hoofs unwetted,
kapioisen kastumatta,
And his feet unsunk in water.
vuohisen vajoumatta.
But the youthful Joukahainen,
Olipa nuori Joukahainen,
He, the puny son of Lapland,
laiha poika lappalainen.
Long had cherished his resentment,
Piti viikoista vihoa,
And had long indeed been envious
ylen kauaista kaetta
Of the aged Väinämöinen,
kera vanhan Väinämöisen,
Of the ever-famous minstrel
päälle laulajan ikuisen.
Then he wrought a mighty crossbow.
Laativi tulisen jousen,
And a splendid bow he fashioned,
jalon kaaren kaunistavi:
And he formed the bow of iron,
kaaren rauasta rakenti,
Overlaid the back with copper.
vaskesta selän valavi;
And with gold inlaid it also,
noita on kullalla kuvaili,
And with silver he adorned it.
hopealla huolitteli.
Where did he obtain the bowstring?
Mistä siihen nauhan saapi,
Whence a cord to match the weapon?
kusta jäntehen tapasi?
Sinews from the elk of Hiisi,
Hiien hirven suoniloista,
And the hempen cord of Lempo.
Lemmon liinanuorasista!
Thus at length the bow was finished.
Sai kaaren kanineheksi,
And the stock was quite completed,
jousen varsin valmihiksi.
And the bow was fair to gaze on,
Kaari on kaunihin näköinen,
And its value matched its beauty.
jousi jonki maksavainen:
At its back a horse was standing,
hevonen selällä seisoi,
On the stock a foal was running,
varsa juoksi vartta myöten,
On the curve a sleeping woman,
kapo kaarella makasi,
At the catch a hare was couching.
jänö jäntimen sijassa.
Shafts of wood he likewise fashioned.
Vuoli piiliä pinosen,
Every arrow triply feathered,
kolmisulkia kokosen:
And the shafts were formed of oakwood,
varret tammesta vanuvi,
And he made the heads of pinewood;
päät tekevi tervaksesta.
Thus the arrows were completed,
Minkä saapi valmihiksi,
And he fixed the feathers on them,
sen sitte sulittelevi
From the swallows' plumage taken.
pääskyn pienillä sulilla,
Likewise from the tails of sparrows.
varpusen vivustimilla.
After this, the points he sharpened.
Karkaeli nuoliansa,
And the arrow-points he poisoned.
puretteli piiliänsä
In the black blood of the serpent,
maon mustissa mujuissa,
In the blood of hissing adders.
käärmehen kähyverissä.
Thus he made his arrows ready,
Sai vasamat valmihiksi,
And his bow was fit for bending,
jousen jänniteltäväksi.
And he watched for Väinämöinen,
Siitä vuotti Väinämöistä,
Waited for Suvantolainen,
saavaksi suvantolaista;
Watched at morning, watched at evenings
vuotti illan, vuotti aamun,
Waited also through the noontide.
vuotti kerran keskipäivän.
Long he watched for Väinämöinen,
Viikon vuotti Väinämöistä,
Waited long, and wearied never,
viikon vuotti, ei väsynyt,
Sitting gazing from the window,
istuellen ikkunoissa,
Or upon the stairs he waited,
valvoen vajojen päissä,
Sometimes lurking by the pathway,
kuunnellen kujan perällä,
Sometimes watching in the meadow,
vahtaellen vainiolla,
On his back his well-filled quiver,
viini nuolia selässä,
'Neath his arm his crossbow ready.
hyvä kaari kainalossa.
Then he waited further onwards.
Vuotteli ulompanaki,
Lurking near another building,
talon toisen tuolla puolla:
On the cape that juts out sharply,
nenässä tulisen niemen,
Where the tongue of land curves outward.
tulikaiskun kainalossa,
Near a waterfall, all foaming.
korvalla tulisen kosken,
Past the banks of sacred rivers.
pyhän virran viertimellä.
And at length one day it happened.
Niin päivänä muutamana,
Very early in the morning,
huomenna moniahana
As he turned his eyes to westward,
loi silmänsä luotehelle,
And he turned his head to eastward
käänti päätä päivän alle;
Something dark he spied on ocean.
keksi mustasen merellä,
Something blue upon the billows.
sinerväisen lainehilla:
"Is a cloud in east arising,
"Onko se iässä pilvi,
Or the dawn of day appearing?"
päivän koite koillisessa?"
In the east no cloud was rising,
Ei ollut iässä pilvi,
Nor the dawn of day appearing.
päivän koite koillisessa:
'Twas the aged Väinämöinen,
oli vanha Väinämöinen,
'Twas the ever-famous minstrel,
laulaja iän-ikuinen,
Who to Pohjola was hasting,
matkoava Pohjolahan,
As to Pimentola he journeyed,
kulkeva Pimentolahan
Mounted on his straw-hued courser.
orihilla olkisella,
Like a pea-stalk in his colour.
hernevarrella hevolla.
Then the youthful Joukahainen,
Tuop' on nuori Joukahainen,
He, the meagre son of Lapland,
laiha poika lappalainen,
Spanned in haste his mighty crossbow.
jou'utti tulisen jousen,
And he aimed the splendid weapon
koppoi kaaren kaunihimman
At the head of Väinämöinen,
pään varalle Väinämöisen,
Thus to kill Suvantolainen.
surmaksi suvantolaisen.
Then his mother came and asked him,
Ennätti emo kysyä,
And the aged one inquired,
vanhempansa tutkaella:
"Wherefore do you span your weapon,
"Kellen jousta jouahutat,
Bending thus the iron crossbow?"
kaarta rauta rauahutat?"
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Tuop' on nuori Joukahainen
Answered in the words which follow.
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Therefore do I span the weapon.
"Tuohon jousta jouahutan,
Bending thus the iron crossbow.
kaarta rauta rauahutan:
For the head of Väinämöinen,
pään varalle Väinämöisen,
Thus to kill Suvantolainen,
surmaksi suvantolaisen.
I will shoot old Väinämöinen,
Ammun vanhan Väinämöisen,
Strike the ever-famous minstrel,
lasken laulajan ikuisen
Through the heart, and through the liver,
läpi syämen, maksan kautta,
'Twixt the shoulders I will shoot him."
halki hartiolihojen."
But his mother straight forbade him,
Emo kielti ampumasta,
And dissuaded him from shooting.
emo kielti ja epäsi:
"Do not shoot at Väinämöinen,
"Elä ammu Väinämöistä,
Do not Kalevalainen slaughter.
kaota kalevalaista!
Of a noble race is Väinö;
Väinö on sukua suurta:
He's my sister's son, my nephew.
lankoni sisaren poika.
"If you shoot at Väinämöinen,
"Ampuisitko Väinämöisen,
And should Kalevalainen slaughter.
kaataisit kalevalaisen,
Gladness from the world will vanish,
ilo ilmalta katoisi,
And from earth will song be banished.
laulu maalta lankeaisi.
In the world is gladness better.
Ilo on ilmalla parempi,
And on earth is song more cheerful,
laulu maalla laatuisampi,
Than to Manala if banished.
kuin onpi Manalan mailla,
And to Tuonela's darkest regions."
noilla Tuonelan tuvilla."
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Tuossa nuori Joukahainen
Paused a moment and reflected,
jo vähän ajattelevi,
And he pondered for an instant,
pikkuisen piättelevi:
Though his hands to shoot were ready,
käsi käski ampumahan,
One would shoot, and one restrained him,
käsi käski, toinen kielti,
But his sinewy fingers forced him.
sormet suoniset pakotti.
And at length these words he uttered,
Virkki viimeinki sanoiksi,
And expressed his own decision:
itse lausui, noin nimesi:
"What if twice from earth in future
"Kaotkohot jos kahesti
Every gladness should be banished?
kaikki ilmaiset ilomme,
Let all songs for ever vanish;
kaikki laulut langetkohot!
I will shoot my arrows, heedless!"
Varsin ammun, en varanne."
Then he spanned the mighty crossbow.
Jännitti tulisen jousen,
And he drew the bow of copper,
veti vaskisen vekaran
And against his left knee bent it,
vasten polvea vasenta,
Steady with his foot he held it,
jalan alta oikeansa.
Took an arrow from his quiver,
Veti viinestä vasaman,
Chose a triple-feathered arrow,
sulan kolmikoipisesta,
Took the strongest of his arrows,
otti nuolen orhe'imman,
Chose the very best among them,
valitsi parahan varren;
Then upon the groove he laid it,
tuon on juonelle asetti,
On the hempen cord he fixed it,
liitti liinajäntehelle.
Then his mighty bow he lifted,
Oikaisi tulisen jousen
And he placed it to his shoulder,
olallehen oikealle,
Ready now to shoot the arrow,
asetaiksen ampumahan,
And to shoot at Väinämöinen.
ampumahan Väinämöistä.
And he spoke the words which follow:
Itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"Do thou strike, O birchwood arrow,
"Iske nyt, koivuinen sakara,
Strike thou in the back, O pinewood.
petäjäinen selkä, lyö'ös,
Twang thy best, O hempen bowstring!
jänne liina, lippaellos!
If my hand is leaning downward,
Min käsi alentanehe,
Let the arrow then strike higher,
sen nuoli ylentäköhön;
If my hand is bending upward,
min käsi ylentänehe,
Let the arrow then strike downward!"
sen nuoli alentakohon!"
Quickly then he drew the trigger,
Lekahutti liipaisinta,
Shot the first among his arrows.
ampui nuolen ensimäisen:
Far too high the shaft flew upward.
se meni kovan ylätse,
High above his head to skyward,
päältä pään on taivahalle,
And it whizzed among the cloudlets,
pilvihin pirajavihin,
Through the scattered clouds it wandered.
hattaroihin pyörivihin.
Thus he shot, in reckless fashion,
Toki ampui, ei totellut.
Shot the second of his arrows.
Ampui toisen nuoliansa:
Far too low the shot flew downwards.
se meni kovan alatse,
Deep in Mother Earth 'twas sunken.
alaisehen maa-emähän;
Earth was almost sunk to Mana,
tahtoi maa manalle mennä,
And the hills of sand were cloven.
hietaharju halkiella.
Then he shot again, a third time,
Ampui kohta kolmannenki:
And the third shaft, straighter flying,
kävi kohti kolmannesti,
In the blue elk's spleen was buried,
sapsohon sinisen hirven
Under aged Väinämöinen,
alta vanhan Väinämöisen;
Thus he shot the straw-hued courser,
ampui olkisen orihin,
Like a pea-stalk in his colour;
hernevartisen hevosen
Through the flesh beneath his shoulder,
läpi länkiluun lihoista,
In the left side deep he pierced him.
kautta kainalon vasemman.
Then the aged Väinämöinen,
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Plunged his fingers in the water,
sormin suistuvi sulahan,
With his hands the waves he parted,
käsin kääntyi lainehesen,
Grasping at the foaming billows,
kourin kuohu'un kohahti
From the blue elk's back he tumbled
selästä sinisen hirven,
From the steed of pea-stalk colour.
hernevartisen hevosen.
Then a mighty wind arising
Nousi siitä suuri tuuli,
Raised upon the sea a billow,
aalto ankara merellä;
And it bore old Väinämöinen,
kantoi vanhan Väinämöisen,
Swimming from the mainland further,
uitteli ulomma maasta
O'er the wide expanse of water,
noille väljille vesille,
Out into the open ocean.
ulapoille auke'ille.
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Siinä nuori Joukahainen
Uttered words of boastful triumph:
itse kielin kerskaeli:
"Now thou ancient Väinämöinen,
"Et sinä, vanha Väinämöinen,
Never while thy life endureth,
enämpi elävin silmin
In the course of all thy lifetime,
sinä ilmoisna ikänä,
While the golden moon is shining,
kuuna kullan valkeana
Walk in Väinölä's fair meadows.
astu Väinölän ahoja,
Or on Kalevala's broad heathlands!
Kalevalan kankahia!
"May you toss for six years running,
"Kupli nyt siellä kuusi vuotta,
Seven long summers ever drifting,
seuro seitsemän kesyttä,
Tossed about for over eight years,
karehi kaheksan vuotta
On the wide expanse of water,
noilla väljillä vesillä,
On the surface of the billows,
lake'illa lainehilla:
Drift for six years like a pine-tree,
vuotta kuusi kuusipuuna,
And for seven years like a fir-tree,
seitsemän petäjäpuuna,
And for eight years like a tree-stump!"
kannon pölkkynä kaheksan!"
Then the house again he entered,
Siitä pistihe sisälle.
And at once his mother asked him,
Sai emo kysyneheksi:
"Have you shot at Väinämöinen?
"Joko ammuit Väinämöisen,
Slaughtered Kaleva's famous offspring?"
kaotit Kalevan poian?"
Then the youthful Joukahainen
Tuop' on nuori Joukahainen
Answered in the words which follow
sanan vastahan sanovi:
"I have shot at Väinämöinen,
"Jo nyt ammuin Väinämöisen
And have o'erthrown Kalevalainen,
ja kaaoin kalevalaisen,
Sent him swimming in the water,
loin on merta luutimahan,
Swept him out upon the billows,
lainetta lakaisemahan.
On the restless waves of ocean
Tuohon lietohon merehen,
Where the waves are wildly tossing,
aivan aaltojen sekahan
And the old man plunged his fingers
sortui ukko sormillehen,
And his palms amid the waters,
kääntyi kämmenyisillehen;
Then upon his side he tumbled,
siitä kyykertyi kylelle,
And upon his back he turned him,
selällehen seisottihe
Drifting o'er the waves of ocean,
meren aaltojen ajella,
Out upon the foaming billows."
meren tyrskyn tyyräellä."
But his mother made him answer,
Tuon emo sanoiksi virkki:
"Very evil hast thou acted,
"Pahoin teit sinä poloinen,
Thus to shoot at Väinämöinen
kun on ammuit Väinämöisen,
And to o'erthrow Kalevalainen.
kaotit kalevalaisen,
Of Suvantola the hero,
Suvantolan suuren miehen,
Kalevala's most famous hero."
Kalevalan kaunihimman!"